Sampling and Data: Introduction

This module provides a brief introduction to the field of statistics, including examples of how these topics shows up in a variety of real-life examples.

Student Learning Outcomes

By the end of this chapter, the student should be able to:

Recognize and differentiate between key terms.
Apply various types of sampling methods to data collection.
Create and interpret frequency tables.

Introduction

You are probably asking yourself the question, "When and where will I use statistics?". If you read any newspaper or watch television, or use the Internet, you will see statistical information. There are statistics about crime, sports, education, politics, and real estate. Typically, when you read a newspaper article or watch a news program on television, you are given sample information. With this information, you may make a decision about the correctness of a statement, claim, or "fact." Statistical methods can help you make the "best educated guess."

Since you will undoubtedly be given statistical information at some point in your life, you need to know some techniques to analyze the information thoughtfully. Think about buying a house or managing a budget. Think about your chosen profession. The fields of economics, business, psychology, education, biology, law, computer science, police science, and early childhood development require at least one course in statistics.

Included in this chapter are the basic ideas and words of probability and statistics. You will soon understand that statistics and probability work together. You will also learn how data are gathered and what "good" data are.

Sampling and Data: Sampling

Gathering information about an entire population often costs too much or is virtually impossible. Instead, we use a sample of the population. A sample should have the same characteristics as the population it is representing. Most statisticians use various methods of random sampling in an attempt to achieve this goal. This section will describe a few of the most common methods.

There are several different methods of random sampling. In each form of random sampling, each member of a population initially has an equal chance of being selected for the sample. Each method has pros and cons. The easiest method to describe is called a simple random sample. Any group of n individuals is equally likely to be chosen by any other group of n individuals if the simple random sampling technique is used. In other words, each sample of the same size has an equal chance of being selected. For example, suppose Lisa wants to form a four-person study group (herself and three other people) from her pre-calculus class, which has 31 members not including Lisa. To choose a simple random sample of size 3 from the other members of her class, Lisa could put all 31 names in a hat, shake the hat, close her eyes, and pick out 3 names. A more technological way is for Lisa to first list the last names of the members of her class together with a two-digit number as shown below.

Class Roster

ID | Name
00 | Anselmo
01 | Bautista
02 | Bayani
03 | Cheng
04 | Cuarismo
05 | Cuningham
06 | Fontecha
07 | Hong
08 | Hoobler
09 | Jiao
10 | Khan
11 | King
12 | Legeny
13 | Lundquist
14 | Macierz
15 | Motogawa
16 | Okimoto
17 | Patel
18 | Price
19 | Quizon
20 | Reyes
21 | Roquero
22 | Roth
23 | Rowell
24 | Salangsang
25 | Slade
26 | Stracher
27 | Tallai
28 | Tran
29 | Wai
30 | Wood

Lisa can either use a table of random numbers (found in many statistics books as well as mathematical handbooks) or a calculator or computer to generate random numbers. For this example, suppose Lisa chooses to generate random numbers from a calculator. The numbers generated are:

.94360
.99832
.14669
.51470
.40581
.73381
.04399

Lisa reads two-digit groups until she has chosen three class members (that is, she reads .94360 as the groups 94, 43, 36, 60). Each random number may only contribute one class member. If she needed to, Lisa could have generated more random numbers.

The random numbers .94360 and .99832 do not contain appropriate two digit numbers. However the third random number, .14669, contains 14 (the fourth random number also contains 14), the fifth random number contains 05, and the seventh random number contains 04. The two-digit number 14 corresponds to Macierz, 05 corresponds to Cunningham, and 04 corresponds to Cuarismo. Besides herself, Lisa's group will consist of Marcierz, and Cunningham, and Cuarismo.

Besides simple random sampling, there are other forms of sampling that involve a chance process for getting the sample. Other well-known random sampling methods are the stratified sample, the cluster sample, and the systematic sample.

To choose a stratified sample, divide the population into groups called strata and then take a proportionate number from each stratum. For example, you could stratify (group) your college population by department and then choose a proportionate simple random sample from each stratum (each department) to get a stratified random sample. To choose a simple random sample from each department, number each member of the first department, number each member of the second department and do the same for the remaining departments. Then use simple random sampling to choose proportionate numbers from the first department and do the same for each of the remaining departments. Those numbers picked from the first department, picked from the second department and so on represent the members who make up the stratified sample.

To choose a cluster sample, divide the population into clusters (groups) and then randomly select some of the clusters. All the members from these clusters are in the cluster sample. For example, if you randomly sample four departments from your college population, the four departments make up the cluster sample. For example, divide your college faculty by department. The departments are the clusters. Number each department and then choose four different numbers using simple random sampling. All members of the four departments with those numbers are the cluster sample.

To choose a systematic sample, randomly select a starting point and take every nth piece of data from a listing of the population. For example, suppose you have to do a phone survey. Your phone book contains 20,000 residence listings. You must choose 400 names for the sample. Number the population 1 - 20,000 and then use a simple random sample to pick a number that represents the first name of the sample. Then choose every 50th name thereafter until you have a total of 400 names (you might have to go back to the of your phone list). Systematic sampling is frequently chosen because it is a simple method.

A type of sampling that is nonrandom is convenience sampling. Convenience sampling involves using results that are readily available. For example, a computer software store conducts a marketing study by interviewing potential customers who happen to be in the store browsing through the available software. The results of convenience sampling may be very good in some cases and highly biased (favors certain outcomes) in others.

Sampling data should be done very carefully. Collecting data carelessly can have devastating results. Surveys mailed to households and then returned may be very biased (for example, they may favor a certain group). It is better for the person conducting the survey to select the sample respondents.

True random sampling is done with replacement. That is, once a member is picked that member goes back into the population and thus may be chosen more than once. However for practical reasons, in most populations, simple random sampling is done without replacement. Surveys are typically done without replacement. That is, a member of the population may be chosen only once. Most samples are taken from large populations and the sample tends to be small in comparison to the population. Since this is the case, sampling without replacement is approximately the same as sampling with replacement because the chance of picking the same individual more than once using with replacement is very low.

For example, in a college population of 10,000 people, suppose you want to randomly pick a sample of 1000 for a survey. For any particular sample of 1000, if you are sampling with replacement,

the chance of picking the first person is 1000 out of 10,000 (0.1000);
the chance of picking a different second person for this sample is 999 out of 10,000 (0.0999);
the chance of picking the same person again is 1 out of 10,000 (very low).

If you are sampling without replacement,

the chance of picking the first person for any particular sample is 1000 out of 10,000 (0.1000);
the chance of picking a different second person is 999 out of 9,999 (0.0999);
you do not replace the first person before picking the next person.

Compare the fractions 999/10,000 and 999/9,999. For accuracy, carry the decimal answers to 4 place decimals. To 4 decimal places, these numbers are equivalent (0.0999).

Sampling without replacement instead of sampling with replacement only becomes a mathematics issue when the population is small which is not that common. For example, if the population is 25 people, the sample is 10 and you are sampling with replacement for any particular sample,

the chance of picking the first person is 10 out of 25 and a different second person is 9 out of 25 (you replace the first person).

If you sample without replacement,

the chance of picking the first person is 10 out of 25 and then the second person (which is different) is 9 out of 24 (you do not replace the first person).

Compare the fractions 9/25 and 9/24. To 4 decimal places, 9/25 = 0.3600 and 9/24 = 0.3750. To 4 decimal places, these numbers are not equivalent.

When you analyze data, it is important to be aware of sampling errors and nonsampling errors. The actual process of sampling causes sampling errors. For example, the sample may not be large enough. Factors not related to the sampling process cause nonsampling errors. A defective counting device can cause a nonsampling error.

In reality, a sample will never be exactly representative of the population so there will always be some sampling error. As a rule, the larger the sample, the smaller the sampling error.

In statistics, a sampling bias is created when a sample is collected from a population and some members of the population are not as likely to be chosen as others (remember, each member of the population should have an equally likely chance of being chosen). When a sampling bias happens, there can be incorrect conclusions drawn about the population that is being studied.

Determine the type of sampling used (simple random, stratified, systematic, cluster, or convenience).

A soccer coach selects 6 players from a group of boys aged 8 to 10, 7 players from a group of boys aged 11 to 12, and 3 players from a group of boys aged 13 to 14 to form a recreational soccer team.
A pollster interviews all human resource personnel in five different high tech companies.
A high school educational researcher interviews 50 high school female teachers and 50 high school male teachers.
A medical researcher interviews every third cancer patient from a list of cancer patients at a local hospital.
A high school counselor uses a computer to generate 50 random numbers and then picks students whose names correspond to the numbers.
A student interviews classmates in his algebra class to determine how many pairs of jeans a student owns, on the average.

stratified
cluster
stratified
systematic
simple random
convenience

If we were to examine two samples representing the same population, even if we used random sampling methods for the samples, they would not be exactly the same. Just as there is variation in data, there is variation in samples. As you become accustomed to sampling, the variability will seem natural.

Suppose ABC College has 10,000 part-time students (the population). We are interested in the average amount of money a part-time student spends on books in the fall term. Asking all 10,000 students is an almost impossible task.

Suppose we take two different samples.

First, we use convenience sampling and survey 10 students from a first term organic chemistry class. Many of these students are taking first term calculus in addition to the organic chemistry class . The amount of money they spend is as follows:

$128
$87
$173
$116
$130
$204
$147
$189
$93
$153

The second sample is taken by using a list from the P.E. department of senior citizens who take P.E. classes and taking every 5th senior citizen on the list, for a total of 10 senior citizens. They spend:

$50
$40
$36
$15
$50
$100
$40
$53
$22
$22

Do you think that either of these samples is representative of (or is characteristic of) the entire 10,000 part-time student population?

No. The first sample probably consists of science-oriented students. Besides the chemistry course, some of them are taking first-term calculus. Books for these classes tend to be expensive. Most of these students are, more than likely, paying more than the average part-time student for their books. The second sample is a group of senior citizens who are, more than likely, taking courses for health and interest. The amount of money they spend on books is probably much less than the average part-time student. Both samples are biased. Also, in both cases, not all students have a chance to be in either sample.

Since these samples are not representative of the entire population, is it wise to use the results to describe the entire population?

No. For these samples, each member of the population did not have an equally likely chance of being chosen.

Now, suppose we take a third sample. We choose ten different part-time students from the disciplines of chemistry, math, English, psychology, sociology, history, nursing, physical education, art, and early childhood development. (We assume that these are the only disciplines in which part-time students at ABC College are enrolled and that an equal number of part-time students are enrolled in each of the disciplines.) Each student is chosen using simple random sampling. Using a calculator, random numbers are generated and a student from a particular discipline is selected if he/she has a corresponding number. The students spend:

$180
$50
$150
$85
$260
$75
$180
$200
$200
$150

Is the sample biased?

The sample is unbiased, but a larger sample would be recommended to increase the likelihood that the sample will be close to representative of the population. However, for a biased sampling technique, even a large sample runs the risk of not being representative of the population.

Students often ask if it is "good enough" to take a sample, instead of surveying the entire population. If the survey is done well, the answer is yes.

Optional Collaborative Classroom Exercise

As a class, determine whether or not the following samples are representative. If they are not, discuss the reasons.

To find the average GPA of all students in a university, use all honor students at the university as the sample.
To find out the most popular cereal among young people under the age of 10, stand outside a large supermarket for three hours and speak to every 20th child under age 10 who enters the supermarket.
To find the average annual income of all adults in the United States, sample U.S. congressmen. Create a cluster sample by considering each state as a stratum (group). By using simple random sampling, select states to be part of the cluster. Then survey every U.S. congressman in the cluster.
To determine the proportion of people taking public transportation to work, survey 20 people in New York City. Conduct the survey by sitting in Central Park on a bench and interviewing every person who sits next to you.
To determine the average cost of a two day stay in a hospital in Massachusetts, survey 100 hospitals across the state using simple random sampling.

Sampling and Data: Variation and Critical Evaluation

Variation in Data

Variation is present in any set of data. For example, 16-ounce cans of beverage may contain more or less than 16 ounces of liquid. In one study, eight 16 ounce cans were measured and produced the following amount (in ounces) of beverage:

15.8
16.1
15.2
14.8
15.8
15.9
16.0
15.5

Measurements of the amount of beverage in a 16-ounce can may vary because different people make the measurements or because the exact amount, 16 ounces of liquid, was not put into the cans. Manufacturers regularly run tests to determine if the amount of beverage in a 16-ounce can falls within the desired range.

Be aware that as you take data, your data may vary somewhat from the data someone else is taking for the same purpose. This is completely natural. However, if two or more of you are taking the same data and get very different results, it is time for you and the others to reevaluate your data-taking methods and your accuracy.

Variation in Samples

It was mentioned previously that two or more samples from the same population, taken randomly, and having close to the same characteristics of the population are different from each other. Suppose Doreen and Jung both decide to study the average amount of time students at their college sleep each night. Doreen and Jung each take samples of 500 students. Doreen uses systematic sampling and Jung uses cluster sampling. Doreen's sample will be different from Jung's sample. Even if Doreen and Jung used the same sampling method, in all likelihood their samples would be different. Neither would be wrong, however.

Think about what contributes to making Doreen's and Jung's samples different.

If Doreen and Jung took larger samples (i.e. the number of data values is increased), their sample results (the average amount of time a student sleeps) might be closer to the actual population average. But still, their samples would be, in all likelihood, different from each other. This variability in samples cannot be stressed enough.

Size of a Sample

The size of a sample (often called the number of observations) is important. The examples you have seen in this book so far have been small. Samples of only a few hundred observations, or even smaller, are sufficient for many purposes. In polling, samples that are from 1200 to 1500 observations are considered large enough and good enough if the survey is random and is well done. You will learn why when you study confidence intervals.

Be aware that many large samples are biased. For example, call-in surveys are invariable biased because people choose to respond or not.

Optional Collaborative Classroom Exercise

Divide into groups of two, three, or four. Your instructor will give each group one 6-sided die. Try this experiment twice. Roll one fair die (6-sided) 20 times. Record the number of ones, twos, threes, fours, fives, and sixes you get below ("frequency" is the number of times a particular face of the die occurs):

First Experiment (20 rolls)

Face on Die | Frequency
1 |
2 |
3 |
4 |
5 |
6 |

Second Experiment (20 rolls)

Face on Die | Frequency
1 |
2 |
3 |
4 |
5 |
6 |

Did the two experiments have the same results? Probably not. If you did the experiment a third time, do you expect the results to be identical to the first or second experiment? (Answer yes or no.) Why or why not?

Which experiment had the correct results? They both did. The job of the statistician is to see through the variability and draw appropriate conclusions.

Critical Evaluation

We need to critically evaluate the statistical studies we read about and analyze before accepting the results of the study. Common problems to be aware of include

Problems with Samples: A sample should be representative of the population. A sample that is not representative of the population is biased. Biased samples that are not representative of the population give results that are inaccurate and not valid.
Self-Selected Samples: Responses only by people who choose to respond, such as call-in surveys are often unreliable.
Sample Size Issues: Samples that are too small may be unreliable. Larger samples are better if possible. In some situations, small samples are unavoidable and can still be used to draw conclusions, even though larger samples are better. Examples: Crash testing cars, medical testing for rare conditions.
Undue influence: Collecting data or asking questions in a way that influences the response.
Non-response or refusal of subject to participate: The collected responses may no longer be representative of the population. Often, people with strong positive or negative opinions may answer surveys, which can affect the results.
Causality: A relationship between two variables does not mean that one causes the other to occur. They may both be related (correlated) because of their relationship through a different variable.
Self-Funded or Self-Interest Studies: A study performed by a person or organization in order to support their claim. Is the study impartial? Read the study carefully to evaluate the work. Do not automatically assume that the study is good but do not automatically assume the study is bad either. Evaluate it on its merits and the work done.
Misleading Use of Data: Improperly displayed graphs, incomplete data, lack of context.
Confounding: When the effects of multiple factors on a response cannot be separated. Confounding makes it difficult or impossible to draw valid conclusions about the effect of each factor.

Preface to "Collaborative Statistics"

This module introduces the Connexions online textbook "Collaborative Statistics" by Barbara Illowsky and Susan Dean.

Welcome to

Collaborative Statistics

, presented by Connexions. The initial section below introduces you to Connexions. If you are familiar with Connexions, please skip to About "Collaborative Statistics."

About Connexions

Connexions Modular ContentConnexions (cnx.org) is an online, open access educational resource dedicated to providing high quality learning materials free online, free in printable PDF format, and at low cost in bound volumes through print-on-demand publishing. The

Collaborative Statistics

textbook is one of many collections available to Connexions users. Each collection is composed of a number of re-usable learning modules written in the Connexions XML markup language. Each module may also be re-used (or 're-purposed') as part of other collections and may be used outside of Connexions. Including

Collaborative Statistics

, Connexions currently offers over 6500 modules and more than 350 collections.

The modules of

Collaborative Statistics

are derived from the original paper version of the textbook under the same title,

Collaborative Statistics

. Each module represents a self-contained concept from the original work. Together, the modules comprise the original textbook.

Re-use and CustomizationThe Creative Commons (CC) Attribution license applies to all Connexions modules. Under this license, any module in Connexions may be used or modified for any purpose as long as proper attribution to the original author(s) is maintained. Connexions' authoring tools make re-use (or re-purposing) easy. Therefore, instructors anywhere are permitted to create customized versions of the

Collaborative Statistics

textbook by editing modules, deleting unneeded modules, and adding their own supplementary modules. Connexions' authoring tools keep track of these changes and maintain the CC license's required attribution to the original authors. This process creates a new collection that can be viewed online, downloaded as a single PDF file, or ordered in any quantity by instructors and students as a low-cost printed textbook. To start building custom collections, please visit the help page, “Create a Collection with Existing Modules”. For a guide to authoring modules, please look at the help page, “Create a Module in Minutes”.

Read the book online, print the PDF, or buy a copy of the book.To browse the

Collaborative Statistics

textbook online, visit the collection home page at cnx.org/content/col10522/latest. You will then have three options.

You may obtain a PDF of the entire textbook to print or view offline by clicking on the “Download PDF” link in the “Content Actions” box.
You may order a bound copy of the collection by clicking on the “Order Printed Copy” button.
You may view the collection modules online by clicking on the “Start >>” link, which takes you to the first module in the collection. You can then navigate through the subsequent modules by using their “Next >>” and “Previous >>” links to move forward and backward in the collection. You can jump to any module in the collection by clicking on that module’s title in the “Collection Contents” box on the left side of the window. If these contents are hidden, make them visible by clicking on “[show table of contents]”.

Accessibility and Section 508 Compliance

For information on general Connexions accessibility features, please visit http://cnx.org/content/m17212/latest/.
For information on accessibility features specific to the Collaborative Statistics textbook, please visit http://cnx.org/content/m17211/latest/.

Version Change History and Errata

For a list of modifications, updates, and corrections, please visit http://cnx.org/content/m17360/latest/.

Adoption and Usage

The Collaborative Statistics collection has been adopted and customized by a number of professors and educators for use in their classes. For a list of known versions and adopters, please visit http://cnx.org/content/m18261/latest/.

About “Collaborative Statistics”

Collaborative Statistics

was written by Barbara Illowsky and Susan Dean, faculty members at De Anza College in Cupertino, California. The textbook was developed over several years and has been used in regular and honors-level classroom settings and in distance learning classes. Courses using this textbook have been articulated by the University of California for transfer of credit. The textbook contains full materials for course offerings, including expository text, examples, labs, homework, and projects. A Teacher’s Guide is currently available in print form and on the Connexions site at http://cnx.org/content/col10547/latest/, and supplemental course materials including additional problem sets and video lectures are available at http://cnx.org/content/col10586/latest/. The on-line text for each of these collections collections will meet the Section 508 standards for accessibility.

An on-line course based on the textbook was also developed by Illowsky and Dean. It has won an award as the best on-line California community college course. The on-line course will be available at a later date as a collection in Connexions, and each lesson in the on-line course will be linked to the on-line textbook chapter. The on-line course will include, in addition to expository text and examples, videos of course lectures in captioned and non-captioned format.

The original preface to the book as written by professors Illowsky and Dean, now follows:

This book is intended for introductory statistics courses being taken by students at two– and four–year colleges who are majoring in fields other than math or engineering. Intermediate algebra is the only prerequisite. The book focuses on applications of statistical knowledge rather than the theory behind it. The text is named

Collaborative Statistics

because students learn best by doing. In fact, they learn best by working in small groups. The old saying “two heads are better than one” truly applies here.

Our emphasis in this text is on four main concepts:

thinking statistically
incorporating technology
working collaboratively
writing thoughtfully

These concepts are integral to our course. Students learn the best by actively participating, not by just watching and listening. Teaching should be highly interactive. Students need to be thoroughly engaged in the learning process in order to make sense of statistical concepts.

Collaborative Statistics

provides techniques for students to write across the curriculum, to collaborate with their peers, to think statistically, and to incorporate technology.

This book takes students step by step. The text is interactive. Therefore, students can immediately apply what they read. Once students have completed the process of problem solving, they can tackle interesting and challenging problems relevant to today’s world. The problems require the students to apply their newly found skills. In addition, technology (TI-83 graphing calculators are highlighted) is incorporated throughout the text and the problems, as well as in the special group activities and projects. The book also contains labs that use real data and practices that lead students step by step through the problem solving process.

At De Anza, along with hundreds of other colleges across the country, the college audience involves a large number of ESL students as well as students from many disciplines. The ESL students, as well as the non-ESL students, have been especially appreciative of this text. They find it extremely readable and understandable.

Collaborative Statistics

has been used in classes that range from 20 to 120 students, and in regular, honor, and distance learning classes.

Susan Dean

Barbara Illowsky

Descriptive Statistics: Displaying Data

This module provides a brief introduction into the ways graphs and charts can be used to provide visual representations of data.

A statistical graph is a tool that helps you learn about the shape or distribution of a sample. The graph can be a more effective way of presenting data than a mass of numbers because we can see where data clusters and where there are only a few data values. Newspapers and the Internet use graphs to show trends and to enable readers to compare facts and figures quickly.

Statisticians often graph data first to get a picture of the data. Then, more formal tools may be applied.

Some of the types of graphs that are used to summarize and organize data are the dot plot, the bar chart, the histogram, the stem-and-leaf plot, the frequency polygon (a type of broken line graph), pie charts, and the boxplot. In this chapter, we will briefly look at stem-and-leaf plots, line graphs and bar graphs. Our emphasis will be on histograms and boxplots.

Descriptive Statistics: Introduction

Student Learning Outcomes

By the end of this chapter, the student should be able to:

Display data graphically and interpret graphs: stemplots, histograms and boxplots.
Recognize, describe, and calculate the measures of location of data: quartiles and percentiles.
Recognize, describe, and calculate the measures of the center of data: mean, median, and mode.
Recognize, describe, and calculate the measures of the spread of data: variance, standard deviation, and range.

Introduction

Once you have collected data, what will you do with it? Data can be described and presented in many different formats. For example, suppose you are interested in buying a house in a particular area. You may have no clue about the house prices, so you might ask your real estate agent to give you a sample data set of prices. Looking at all the prices in the sample often is overwhelming. A better way might be to look at the median price and the variation of prices. The median and variation are just two ways that you will learn to describe data. Your agent might also provide you with a graph of the data.

In this chapter, you will study numerical and graphical ways to describe and display your data. This area of statistics is called "Descriptive Statistics". You will learn to calculate, and even more importantly, to interpret these measurements and graphs.

Collaborative Statistics: Student Welcome Letter

Dear Student:

Have you heard others say, “You’re taking statistics? That’s the hardest course I ever took!” They say that, because they probably spent the entire course confused and struggling. They were probably lectured to and never had the chance to experience the subject. You will not have that problem. Let’s find out why.

There is a Chinese Proverb that describes our feelings about the field of statistics:

I HEAR, AND I FORGET

I SEE, AND I REMEMBER

I DO, AND I UNDERSTAND

Statistics is a “do” field. In order to learn it, you must “do” it. We have structured this book so that you will have hands-on experiences. They will enable you to truly understand the concepts instead of merely going through the requirements for the course.

What makes this book different from other texts? First, we have eliminated the drudgery of tedious calculations. You might be using computers or graphing calculators so that you do not need to struggle with algebraic manipulations. Second, this course is taught as a collaborative activity. With others in your class, you will work toward the common goal of learning this material.

Here are some hints for success in your class:

Work hard and work every night.
Form a study group and learn together.
Don’t get discouraged - you can do it!
As you solve problems, ask yourself, “Does this answer make sense?”
Many statistics words have the same meaning as in everyday English.
Go to your teacher for help as soon as you need it.
Don’t get behind.
Read the newspaper and ask yourself, “Does this article make sense?”
Draw pictures - they truly help!

Good luck and don’t give up!

Sincerely,
Susan Dean and Barbara Illowsky

De Anza College
21250 Stevens Creek Blvd.
Cupertino, California 95014

Collaborative Statistics: Author Acknowledgements

This module contains the author acknowledgements for the Collaborative Statistics textbook/collection.

For this second edition, we appreciate the tremendous feedback from De Anza College colleagues and students, as well as from the dozens of faculty around the world who taught out of the first and preliminary editions. We have updated Collaborative Statistics with contributions from many faculty and students. We especially thank Roberta Bloom, who wrote new problems and additional text.

So many students and colleagues have contributed to the text, both the hard copy and open version. We thank the following people for their contributions to the first and/or second editions.

At De Anza College:
Dr. Inna Grushko (deceased), who wrote the glossary; Diane Mathios, who checked every homework problem in the first edition; Kathy Plum, Lenore Desilets, Charles Klein, Janice Hector, Frank Snow, Dr. Lisa Markus, Dr. Vladimir Logvinenko (deceased), Mo Geraghty, Rupinder Sekhon, Javier Rueda, Carol Olmstead; Also, Dr. Jim Lucas and Valerie Hauber of De Anza’s Office of Institutional Research, Mary Jo Kane of Health Services; and the thousands of students who have used this text. Many of the students gave us permission to include their outstanding word problems as homework.

Additional thanks:
Dr. Larry Green of Lake Tahoe Community College, Terrie Teegarden of San Diego Mesa College, Ann Flanigan of Kapiolani Community College, Birgit Aquilonius of West Valley College.

The conversion from a for-profit hard copy text to a free open textbook is the result of many individuals and organizations. We particularly thank Dr. Martha Kanter, Hal Plotkin, Dr. Judy Baker, Dr. Robert Maxfield of Maxfield Foundation, Hewlett Foundation, and Connexions.

Finally, we owe much to Frank, Jeffrey, and Jessica Dean and to Dan, Rachel, Matthew, and Rebecca Illowsky, who encouraged us to continue with our work and who had to hear more than their share of “I’m sorry, I can’t” and “Just a minute, I’m working.”

Hypothesis Testing of Single Mean and Single Proportion: Introduction

Student Learning Outcomes

By the end of this chapter, the student should be able to:

Differentiate between Type I and Type II Errors
Describe hypothesis testing in general and in practice
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for a single population mean, population standard deviation known.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for a single population mean, population standard deviation unknown.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for a single population proportion.

Introduction

One job of a statistician is to make statistical inferences about populations based on samples taken from the population. Confidence intervals are one way to estimate a population parameter. Another way to make a statistical inference is to make a decision about a parameter. For instance, a car dealer advertises that its new small truck gets 35 miles per gallon, on the average. A tutoring service claims that its method of tutoring helps 90% of its students get an A or a B. A company says that women managers in their company earn an average of $60,000 per year.

A statistician will make a decision about these claims. This process is called "hypothesis testing." A hypothesis test involves collecting data from a sample and evaluating the data. Then, the statistician makes a decision as to whether or not there is sufficient evidence based upon analyses of the data, to reject the null hypothesis.

In this chapter, you will conduct hypothesis tests on single means and single proportions. You will also learn about the errors associated with these tests.

Hypothesis testing consists of two contradictory hypotheses or statements, a decision based on the data, and a conclusion. To perform a hypothesis test, a statistician will:

Set up two contradictory hypotheses.
Collect sample data (in homework problems, the data or summary statistics will be given to you).
Determine the correct distribution to perform the hypothesis test.
Analyze sample data by performing the calculations that ultimately will allow you to reject or fail to reject the null hypothesis.
Make a decision and write a meaningful conclusion.

To do the hypothesis test homework problems for this chapter and later chapters, make copies of the appropriate special solution sheets. See the Table of Contents topic "Solution Sheets".

Hypothesis Testing: Two Population Means and Two Population Proportions: Introduction

Student Learning Outcomes

By the end of this chapter, the student should be able to:

Classify hypothesis tests by type.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for two population means, population standard deviations known.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for two population means, population standard deviations unknown.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for two population proportions.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests for matched or paired samples.

Introduction

Studies often compare two groups. For example, researchers are interested in the effect aspirin has in preventing heart attacks. Over the last few years, newspapers and magazines have reported about various aspirin studies involving two groups. Typically, one group is given aspirin and the other group is given a placebo. Then, the heart attack rate is studied over several years.

There are other situations that deal with the comparison of two groups. For example, studies compare various diet and exercise programs. Politicians compare the proportion of individuals from different income brackets who might vote for them. Students are interested in whether SAT or GRE preparatory courses really help raise their scores.

In the previous chapter, you learned to conduct hypothesis tests on single means and single proportions. You will expand upon that in this chapter. You will compare two means or two proportions to each other. The general procedure is still the same, just expanded.

To compare two means or two proportions, you work with two groups. The groups are classified either as independent or matched pairs. Independent groups mean that the two samples taken are independent, that is, sample values selected from one population are not related in any way to sample values selected from the other population. Matched pairs consist of two samples that are dependent. The parameter tested using matched pairs is the population mean. The parameters tested using independent groups are either population means or population proportions.

This chapter relies on either a calculator or a computer to calculate the degrees of freedom, the test statistics, and p-values. TI-83+ and TI-84 instructions are included as well as the test statistic formulas. When using the TI-83+/TI-84 calculators, we do not need to separate two population means, independent groups, population variances unknown into large and small sample sizes. However, most statistical computer software has the ability to differentiate these tests.

This chapter deals with the following hypothesis tests:

Independent groups (samples are independent)

Test of two population means.
Test of two population proportions.

Matched or paired samples (samples are dependent)

Becomes a test of one population mean.

The Chi-Square Distribution: Introduction

This module provides an introduction to Chi-Square Distribution as a part of Collaborative Statistics collection (col10522) by Barbara Illowsky and Susan Dean.

Student Learning Outcomes

By the end of this chapter, the student should be able to:

Interpret the chi-square probability distribution as the sample size changes.
Conduct and interpret chi-square goodness-of-fit hypothesis tests.
Conduct and interpret chi-square test of independence hypothesis tests.
Conduct and interpret chi-square homogeneity hypothesis tests.
Conduct and interpret chi-square single variance hypothesis tests.

Introduction

Have you ever wondered if lottery numbers were evenly distributed or if some numbers occurred with a greater frequency? How about if the types of movies people preferred were different across different age groups? What about if a coffee machine was dispensing approximately the same amount of coffee each time? You could answer these questions by conducting a hypothesis test.

You will now study a new distribution, one that is used to determine the answers to the above examples. This distribution is called the Chi-square distribution.

In this chapter, you will learn the three major applications of the Chi-square distribution:

The goodness-of-fit test, which determines if data fit a particular distribution, such as with the lottery example
The test of independence, which determines if events are independent, such as with the movie example
The test of a single variance, which tests variability, such as with the coffee example

Though the Chi-square calculations depend on calculators or computers for most of the calculations, there is a table available (see the Table of Contents 15. Tables). TI-83+ and TI-84 calculator instructions are included in the text.

Optional Collaborative Classroom Activity

Look in the sports section of a newspaper or on the Internet for some sports data (baseball averages, basketball scores, golf tournament scores, football odds, swimming times, etc.). Plot a histogram and a boxplot using your data. See if you can determine a probability distribution that your data fits. Have a discussion with the class about your choice.

F Distribution and One-Way ANOVA: Introduction

This module provides a brief introduction on handling hypothesis tests with two means by the one-way Analysis of Variance (One-Way ANOVA), F Distribution, and the Test of Two Variances statistical analysis.

Student Learning Outcomes

By the end of this chapter, the student should be able to:

Interpret the F probability distribution as the number of groups and the sample size change.
Discuss two uses for the F distribution: One-Way ANOVA and the test of two variances.
Conduct and interpret One-Way ANOVA.
Conduct and interpret hypothesis tests of two variances.

Introduction

Many statistical applications in psychology, social science, business administration, and the natural sciences involve several groups. For example, an environmentalist is interested in knowing if the average amount of pollution varies in several bodies of water. A sociologist is interested in knowing if the amount of income a person earns varies according to his or her upbringing. A consumer looking for a new car might compare the average gas mileage of several models.

For hypothesis tests involving more than two averages, statisticians have developed a method called Analysis of Variance" (abbreviated ANOVA). In this chapter, you will study the simplest form of ANOVA called single factor or One-Way ANOVA. You will also study the F distribution, used for One-Way ANOVA, and the test of two variances. This is just a very brief overview of One-Way ANOVA. You will study this topic in much greater detail in future statistics courses.

One-Way ANOVA, as it is presented here, relies heavily on a calculator or computer.
For further information about One-Way ANOVA, use the online link ANOVA. Use the back button to return here. (The url is http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Analysis_of_variance.)

Collaborative Statistics: Projects: Hypothesis Testing Article

In this project, students will identify real-world examples of hypothesis testing in the media. Students will then conduct their own survey and compare results.

Student Learning Objectives

The student will identify a hypothesis testing problem in print.
The student will conduct a survey to verify or dispute the results of the hypothesis test.
The student will summarize the article, analysis, and conclusions in a report.

Instructions

As you complete each task below, check it off. Answer all questions in your summary.

Find an article in a newspaper, magazine or on the internet which makes a claim about ONE population mean or ONE population proportion. The claim may be based upon a survey that the article was reporting on. Decide whether this claim is the null or alternate hypothesis.
Copy or print out the article and include a copy in your project, along with the source.
State how you will collect your data. (Convenience sampling is not acceptable.)
Conduct your survey. You must have more than 50 responses in your sample. When you hand in your final project, attach the tally sheet or the packet of questionnaires that you used to collect data. Your data must be real.
State the statistics that are a result of your data collection: sample size, sample mean, and sample standard deviation, OR sample size and number of successes.
Make 2 copies of the appropriate solution sheet.
Record the hypothesis test on the solution sheet, based on your experiment. Do a DRAFT solution first on one of the solution sheets and check it over carefully. Have a classmate check your solution to see if it is done correctly. Make your decision using a 5% level of significance. Include the 95% confidence interval on the solution sheet.
Create a graph that illustrates your data. This may be a pie or bar chart or may be a histogram or box plot, depending on the nature of your data. Produce a graph that makes sense for your data and gives useful visual information about your data. You may need to look at several types of graphs before you decide which is the most appropriate for the type of data in your project.
Write your summary (in complete sentences and paragraphs, with proper grammar and correct spelling) that describes the project. The summary MUST include: Brief discussion of the article, including the source.
Statement of the claim made in the article (one of the hypotheses).
Detailed description of how, where, and when you collected the data, including the sampling technique. Did you use cluster, stratified, systematic, or simple random sampling (using a random number generator)? As stated above, convenience sampling is not acceptable.
Conclusion about the article claim in light of your hypothesis test. This is the conclusion of your hypothesis test, stated in words, in the context of the situation in your project in sentence form, as if you were writing this conclusion for a non-statistician.
Sentence interpreting your confidence interval in the context of the situation in your project.

Assignment Checklist

Turn in the following typed (12 point) and stapled packet for your final project:

Cover sheet containing your name(s), class time, and the name of your study.
Summary, which includes all items listed on summary checklist.
Solution sheet neatly and completely filled out. The solution sheet does not need to be typed.
Graphic representation of your data, created following the guidelines discussed above. Include only graphs which are appropriate and useful.
Raw data collected AND a table summarizing the sample data (n, xbar and s; or x, n, and p’, as appropriate for your hypotheses). The raw data does not need to be typed, but the summary does. Hand in the data as you collected it. (Either attach your tally sheet or an envelope containing your questionnaires.)

Collaborative Statistics: Projects: Bivariate Data, Linear Regression and Univariate Data

Student Learning Objectives

The students will collect a bivariate data sample through the use of appropriate sampling techniques.
The student will attempt to fit the data to a linear model.
The student will determine the appropriateness of linear fit of the model.
The student will analyze and graph univariate data.

Instructions

As you complete each task below, check it off. Answer all questions in your introduction or summary.
Check your course calendar for intermediate and final due dates.
Graphs may be constructed by hand or by computer, unless your instructor informs you otherwise. All graphs must be neat and accurate.
All other responses must be done on the computer.
Neatness and quality of explanations are used to determine your final grade.

Part I: Bivariate Data

Introduction

State the bivariate data your group is going to study.

Here are two examples, but you may NOT use them: height vs. weight and age vs. running distance.

Describe how your group is going to collect the data (for instance, collect data from the web, survey students on campus).
Describe your sampling technique in detail. Use cluster, stratified, systematic, or simple random sampling (using a random number generator) sampling. Convenience sampling is NOT acceptable.
Conduct your survey. Your number of pairs must be at least 30.
Print out a copy of your data.

Analysis

On a separate sheet of paper construct a scatter plot of the data. Label and scale both axes.
State the least squares line and the correlation coefficient.
On your scatter plot, in a different color, construct the least squares line.
Is the correlation coefficient significant? Explain and show how you determined this.
Interpret the slope of the linear regression line in the context of the data in your project. Relate the explanation to your data, and quantify what the slope tells you.
Does the regression line seem to fit the data? Why or why not? If the data does not seem to be linear, explain if any other model seems to fit the data better.
Are there any outliers? If so, what are they? Show your work in how you used the potential outlier formula in the Linear Regression and Correlation chapter (since you have bivariate data) to determine whether or not any pairs might be outliers.

Part II: Univariate Data

In this section, you will use the data for ONE variable only. Pick the variable that is more interesting to analyze. For example: if your independent variable is sequential data such as year with 30 years and one piece of data per year, your x-values might be 1971, 1972, 1973, 1974, …, 2000. This would not be interesting to analyze. In that case, choose to use the dependent variable to analyze for this part of the project.

Summarize your data in a chart with columns showing data value, frequency, relative frequency, and cumulative relative frequency.
Answer the following, rounded to 2 decimal places: Sample mean =
Sample standard deviation =
First quartile =
Third quartile =
Median =
70th percentile =
Value that is 2 standard deviations above the mean =
Value that is 1.5 standard deviations below the mean =

Construct a histogram displaying your data. Group your data into 6 – 10 intervals of equal width. Pick regularly spaced intervals that make sense in relation to your data. For example, do NOT group data by age as 20-26,27-33,34-40,41-47,48-54,55-61 . . . Instead, maybe use age groups 19.5-24.5, 24.5-29.5, . . . or 19.5-29.5, 29.5-39.5, 39.5-49.5, . . .
In complete sentences, describe the shape of your histogram.
Are there any potential outliers? Which values are they? Show your work and calculations as to how you used the potential outlier formula in chapter 2 (since you are now using univariate data) to determine which values might be outliers.
Construct a box plot of your data.
Does the middle 50% of your data appear to be concentrated together or spread out? Explain how you determined this.
Looking at both the histogram AND the box plot, discuss the distribution of your data. For example: how does the spread of the middle 50% of your data compare to the spread of the rest of the data represented in the box plot; how does this correspond to your description of the shape of the histogram; how does the graphical display show any outliers you may have found; does the histogram show any gaps in the data that are not visible in the box plot; are there any interesting features of your data that you should point out.

Due Dates

Part I, Intro: __________ (keep a copy for your records)
Part I, Analysis: __________ (keep a copy for your records)
Entire Project, typed and stapled: __________ Cover sheet: names, class time, and name of your study.
Part I: label the sections “Intro” and “Analysis.”
Part II:
Summary page containing several paragraphs written in complete sentences describing the experiment, including what you studied and how you collected your data. The summary page should also include answers to ALL the questions asked above.
All graphs requested in the project.
All calculations requested to support questions in data.
Description: what you learned by doing this project, what challenges you had, how you overcame the challenges.

Include answers to ALL questions asked, even if not explicitly repeated in the items above.

Collaborative Statistics: Projects: Hypothesis Testing Word Problem

In this project, students will write, edit, and solve a hypothesis testing word problem.

Student Learning Objectives

The student will write, edit, and solve a hypothesis testing word problem.

Instructions

Write an original hypothesis testing problem for either ONE population mean or ONE population proportion. As you complete each task, check it off. Answer all questions in your summary. Look at the homework for the Hypothesis Testing: Single Mean and Single Proportion chapter for examples (poems, two acts of a play, a work related problem). The problems with names attached to them are problems written by students in past quarters. Some other examples that are not in the homework include: a soccer hypothesis testing poster, a cartoon, a news reports, a children’s story, a song.

Your problem must be original and creative. It also must be in proper English. If English is difficult for you, have someone edit your problem.
Your problem must be at least ½ page, typed and singled spaced. This DOES NOT include the data. Data will make the problem longer and that is fine. For this problem, the data and story may be real or fictional.
In the narrative of the problem, make it very clear what the null and alternative hypotheses are.
Your sample size must be LARGER THAN 50 (even if it is fictional).
State in your problem how you will collect your data.
Include your data with your word problem.
State the statistics that are a result of your data collection: sample size, sample mean, and sample standard deviation, OR sample size and number of successes.
Create a graph that illustrates your problem. This may be a pie or bar chart or may be a histogram or box plot, depending on the nature of your data. Produce a graph that makes sense for your data and gives useful visual information about your data. You may need to look at several types of graphs before you decide which is the most appropriate for your problem.
Make 2 copies of the appropriate solution sheet.
Record the hypothesis test on the solution sheet, based on your problem. Do a DRAFT solution first on one of the solution sheets and check it over carefully. Make your decision using a 5% level of significance. Include the 95% confidence interval on the solution

Assignment Checklist

You need to turn in the following typed (12 point) and stapled packet for your final project:

Cover sheet containing your name, the name of your problem, and the date
The problem
Data for the problem
Solution sheet neatly and completely filled out. The solution sheet does not need to be typed.
Graphic representation of the data, created following the guidelines discussed above. Include only graphs that are appropriate and useful.
Sentences interpreting the results of the hypothesis test and the confidence interval in the context of the situation in the project.

Collaborative Statistics: Additional Resources

This module catalogs several of the resources available for teachers and students using the Collaborative Statistics (col10522) textbook and its derivatives. This module provides links to the complementary teacher's guide, supplemental materials including video lectures and additional problem sets, accessibility information, collection version history and errata, and a list of related works and teachers who have adopted them for their courses.

Additional Resources Currently Available

Glossary
View or Download This Textbook Online
Collaborative Statistics Teacher's Guide
Supplemental Materials
Video Lectures
Version History
Textbook Adoption and Usage
Additional Technologies and Notes
Accessibility and Section 508 Compliance

The following section describes some additional resources for learners and educators. These modules and collections are all available on the Connexions website (http://cnx.org/) and can be viewed online, downloaded, printed, or ordered as appropriate.

GlossaryThis module contains the entire glossary for the Collaborative Statistics textbook collection (col10522) since its initial release on 15 July 2008. The glossary is located at http://cnx.org/content/m16129/latest/.

Below are links to additional resources:
Link to the Statistics Glossary by Dr. Philip Stark, UC Berkeley

http://

statistics.berkeley.edu/~stark/SticiGui/Text/gloss.htm

Link to Wikipedia

http://

http://www.wikipedia.org/

(Search on "Glossary of probability and statistics.")

View or Download This Textbook OnlineThe complete contents of this book are available at no cost on the Connexions website at http://cnx.org/content/col10522/latest/. Anybody can view this content free of charge either as an online e-book or a downloadable PDF file. A low-cost printed version of this textbook is also available here.

Collaborative Statistics Teacher's GuideA complementary Teacher's Guide for Collaborative statistics is available through Connexions at http://cnx.org/content/col10547/latest/. The Teacher's Guide includes suggestions for presenting concepts found throughout the book as well as recommended homework assignments. A low-cost printed version of this textbook is also available here.

Supplemental MaterialsThis companion to Collaborative Statistics provides a number of additional resources for use by students and instructors based on the award winning Elementary Statistics Sofia online course, also by textbook authors Barbara Illowsky and Susan Dean. This content is designed to complement the textbook by providing video tutorials, course management materials, and sample problem sets. The Supplemental Materials collection can be found at http://cnx.org/content/col10586/latest/.

Video Lectures

Video Lecture 1: Sampling and Data
Video Lecture 2: Descriptive Statistics
Video Lecture 3: Probability Topics
Video Lecture 4: Discrete Distributions
Video Lecture 5: Continuous Random Variables
Video Lecture 6: The Normal Distribution
Video Lecture 7: The Central Limit Theorem
Video Lecture 8: Confidence Intervals
Video Lecture 9: Hypothesis Testing with a Single Mean
Video Lecture 10: Hypothesis Testing with Two Means
Video Lecture 11: The Chi-Square Distribution
Video Lecture 12: Linear Regression and Correlation

Version HistoryThis module contains a listing of changes, updates, and corrections made to the Collaborative Statistics textbook collection (col10522) since its initial release on 15 July 2008. The Version History is located at http://cnx.org/content/m17360/latest/.

Textbook Adoption and UsageThis module is designed to track the various derivations of the Collaborative Statistics textbook and its various companion resources, as well as keep track of educators who have adopted various versions for their courses. New adopters are encouraged to provide their contact information and describe how they will use this book for their courses. The goal is to provide a list that will allow educators using this book to collaborate, share ideas, and make suggestions for future development of this text. The Adoption and Usage module is located at http://cnx.org/content/m18261/latest/.

Additional TechnologiesIn order to provide the most flexible learning resources possible, we invite collaboration from all instructors wishing to create customized versions of this content for use with other technologies. For instance, you may be interested in creating a set of instructions similar to this collection's calculator notes. If you would like to contribute to this collection, please use the contact the authors with any ideas or materials you have created.

Accessibility and Section 508 Compliance

For information on general Connexions accessibility features, please visit http://cnx.org/content/m17212/latest/.
For information on accessibility features specific to the Collaborative Statistics textbook, please visit http://cnx.org/content/m17211/latest/.